If you were to choose a cultural work at random-
-A fiction book, a movie, a poem or a song-
-Is the chance that something in it can be tracked all the way back to antiquity.
We often see antiquity as the starting point for our modern history-
-Where democracy, science and Western culture arise.
But man has been around for over 200,000 years.
The ancient Greeks have clear ideas on how to behave.
It can be seen in the stories you tell.
A red thread through the Greek literature is to think about:
"How does it look?"
"Will people remember me?"
The worst thing you can do in antiquity is getting hybris.
Not to be moderate but believe that you are as good as the gods.
Then you suffer from nemesis, punishment from above.
Punishment is never fun.
As guidance you have the myths-
-Som with their stories explain the world.
One of the myth's functions is to answer these big questions.
Where does everything come from?
What is the meaning of everything?
How is the universe interconnected, the world of gods and people?
A variety of issues of this kind are dealt with in the myths.
They can also be used to amuse.
These are fantastic stories.
When you read them today you are still taken by them.
One of them is the starting point for our Western literature - the Iliad.
Where does literature start?
It always starts with the Iliad.
The Iliad is an epic, a longer story written in verse.
Together with the Odyssey, it contains 28,000 verses.
An epic takes place in the bygone time
-and the Iliad attracts during the Trojan War in the 13th century BC-
-Sid before the time we count as antiquity.
It is usually said that it is written down by Homer in the 7th century BC.
Book Poiler Iliad:
The Iliad takes place during the tenth and last year of the Trojan war.
The Greeks have besieged the city of Troja.
We meet people as well as gods.
The best fighter of the Greeks, Achilles, comes into trouble with agamemnon-
-and gets so angry that he refuses to fight-
-Ag until Hektor, the prince of Troja, kills one of Achille's best friends.
Then he takes to weapons again and chases Hektor around the city walls-
-What he kills him.
Achilles brings with him and violates the body of the dead prince.
The Iliad takes place in a real time but also in a mythological time.
It is a fantasy product "based on a true story".
The Iliad does not depict the beginning or the end of the Trojan war.
It also does not have the exciting story of the Trojan horse.
Instead, the Iliad has another theme - Achilles and his anger.
Here we see Brad Pitt as Achilles.
He doesn't look so a little angry.
I interpret the Iliad as a problematization of a world-
-which is filled with war and rape-
-And as an illustration of how unsustainable it is as a social form.
Ancient Greece was a society where violence was constantly present.
The vast majority of adult men could count with-
-stories that one combines live in the actual conduct-
-ur The huge storage room you have of these rhythm combinations.
Having the same rhythm combination through a whole work is called a bound verse.
So it is with the hexameter of the Iliad.
Here the first verse.
Notice that we already here hear about Achilles and his anger.
Sing, o goddess about the wrath that burned with Peliden Achilles.
Do you hear the rhythm?
It goes like this.
Women Didi Women Didi Dam Didi Dame Didi Dam Didi Dam.
So it should sound, over and over again in over 28,000 verses.
The Iliad also contains so -called
epithetic
-Where you tell about the characters' traits before their name.
"The fast -footed Achilles."
"The Helmet Bronze Hector."
"The arrow -loving artemis."
The standing epithets helped the listener and singer to remember-
The drama is known through the tragedy.
The tragedy is this spectacle that is set up-
-At the annual festival in Athens the so -called.
Dionysos Festival.
People come from all over the Greek island world, sometimes up to 30,000.
The ancient Greek theater takes place outdoors-
-and is built on a slope with the stage at the bottom-
-and the spectators in a semicircle.
One of the most famous tragedies played-
-As "Antigone" by the playwright Sofokles.
Think about how our father went abrasive and despised in ruin-
-and for his crime as himself he brought in the day-
-With your own hand drove their eyes out.
We have epic where our epic is included as developing into fiction.
The drama is the basis for theater, television and film.
In both, action is crucial.
It also comes a third form of literary design-
-What does not focus on events, but on a feeling.
We are talking about the lyric, the basis for poetry.
It is almost always presented to music and it has been named ...
... from this instrument - a lyre.
One of ancient great poets is Sapfo.
Here we see her think.
Although SAPFO had a great impact on the history of literary
-Found very little of her work preserved.
We must remember that it is over 2,500 years since she lived.
Her poems have no names but are usually called fragment-
-To they have been preserved as parts and loose pieces.
In modern times, many have liked it.
You have liked the fragment style.
There is a lot of room to interpret and enter yourself.
It has probably contributed to the attraction.
There is room to project their own thoughts and dreams.
The lyric is the third and last leg next to the epic and drama-
-On the ancient pallet where much of today's literature rests.
Given that the Greeks find the democracy, philosophy-
-and much of the literature we have today, so you disregard-
-Th a thing that enabled the production of culture and thought-
-Where that someone else did the hard job.
It's the slaves.
The free men, atenna-
-has the opportunity to devote to philosophy and literature-
-This to have to go to work.
A culture that has slave-
-Builds on a human view where everyone is not equal.
Some people are like items that you can change and sell and buy-
-Preatic as with a chair, bicycle or sweater today.